We have a photograph which shows a banquet thrown in Reif's honor to celebrate the end of all disease.
It was even announced in the media.
And then, years later, all these people that were at this banquet in honor of Reif denied even knowing it.
Reif's honor to celebrate the end of all disease.
By all accounts, those who knew Royal Raymond Reif considered him to be a scientific genius.
His greatest accomplishment was the discovery and development of a cure for cancer and for most infectious diseases during a span of 18 years' work in San Diego in the 1920s and 30s.
Reif invented a series of super microscopes which allowed him to see live microbes as small as a virus, an ability considered impossible even today.
Using these highly advanced optical instruments, Royal Reif was able to determine, by direct observation, the presence of a microorganism in cancer tumors.
He named it the BX virus.
Reif then went on to create another unique innovation, one that worked in conjunction with his brilliant microscopes, the Reif beam ray instrument, a device that could destroy any viral or bacterial microorganism with electrical pulses tuned to a specific frequency, an unprecedented way of fighting the infectious agents of disease without drugs.
Given the monopolistic nature of the developing medical establishment in America at that time, the presentation of this drugless technique for treating a multitude of diseases ensured the demise of Reif's work.
Over 70 years later, people are still trying to piece together what happened and attempt to recreate Royal Raymond Reif's lost technology.
The annual International Reif Conference.
The conference is excellent. We have people here from Japan, New Zealand, obviously Canada, England, South Africa. It's just growing.
There are things being done from my understanding. There's a bill before Congress, United States Congress, that would allow, if passed, would allow licensed practitioners to use this technology as they suffered.
And I hope we're moving that way.
Originally, I read the cancer cure that worked by Barry Limes. And because of my medical background, I had the opportunity to go through all the research that was bibliographed from the 1930s and 1940s.
And it's all there. It's incredible. It's all there. It's plain to say, and nobody knows about it. It's hidden. It's buried. We'll spring it out to the open.
One of the speakers at the conference, a Canadian researcher, Jason Rengas, has been researching the Reif story for years.
Well, when we first learned of the Reif story, we quickly found that there was no consensus in some of the details of the story. Every time you hear this story, it's different.
So what we wanted to do is acquire as much accurate information as we could possibly get.
And over the years, we've accumulated letters, photographs, lab notes, newspaper articles, and we've tried to the best of our ability to bring some sort of order and consensus out of all this information.
In 1944, the Franklin Institute and the Smithsonian both published in their prestigious scientific journals a story of emerging technology in the field of optics.
The article entitled The New Microscopes presented several instruments that promised to significantly advance the field of microbiology.
Introduced in this article was the now famous electron microscope with its extreme magnifying capabilities.
Also, the Reif universal microscope was given a detailed and a thorough accounting.
Included in this article were three photomicrographs taken through Reif's revolutionary optical instrument. Nothing from that period could match the resolution apparent in these photomicrographs.
And these pictures were taken ten years previous to their publication in 1944.
So when I saw this picture in the Smithsonian Institute report, I realized that this was a microscope that I would like to have.
In our searching through some of the documents that were recovered on the Reif story, we came across the name of Professor John Hubbard.
Now in 1945, Professor Hubbard was just a medical student and he read the article in the Journal of the Smithsonian Institute about the Reif microscope and was so impressed that he wanted to find out more.
So in 1949, he wrote to Reif and to all the microscope companies asking for more information on this microscope.
Now he didn't find anything, but later in the 1970s, when he was a professor, he read another article that reawakened the Reif story by Christopher Byrd and he picked up the chase again and accumulated a number of documents that he shared with us.
Recognizing Reif's photographs as extraordinary, Dr. Hubbard sought another expert opinion.
So I went over to Don Parsons one day and I showed him a copy of these pictures and I asked him his opinion about them.
And immediately, well these are electron microscopes, so what? I told him no, they then made the Reif microscope back and he immediately, this is fraudulent.
That was his immediate reaction. I pointed out that these had been made long before. Before electron microscopes had come on the scene and pardon the glasses just a minute, but I would like to hold up.
You all might be interested in the most recent issue of advances in imaging and electron physics, volume 115, and if you go back to the page 287, you will get a short synopsis of the early history of the electron microscopes.
And you can see what the status of electron microscopy was at that time. Fellas, there wasn't a chance, not even if you wanted to be a plagiarist.
You couldn't possibly have done with an electron microscope the pictures that are in that report. No possibility.
People like Reif who come up with technologies, inventions that truly do change society, they ran up against the scientific paradigm shift, that you have to bring the scientific community through the shift.
And when, if the scientific community allows that to happen, a lot of people lose their jobs, top people lose their positions at universities because their field becomes irrelevant overnight.
And science has the hardest time allowing this to happen. It usually takes 50-100 years for these kinds of paradigms to happen. And I think that's what's happening with Reif.
It will come out. It'll take 50-100 years before the scientific community, the vested interests, the money, allow it or force to bring it to the surface.
Well, Reif's lab was one of the most advanced labs in the world at that time. He was equipped to design, build and operate virtually any type of scientific instrument that he needed.
He was able to perform experiments that few other people could do because they lacked facilities.
Absolutely ingenious. You don't question about it. His touch for things. Did you ever see a machinist or a mechanic who was more perfect than he is on their head? And you don't recognize it. One of the greatest men in this country, Mr. Timkin.
In 1913, Henry Timkin was president of one of the most prosperous industries in America, the Timkin Roller Bearing Company. His factory, in Canton, Ohio, produced the tens of millions of ball bearings that kept the wheels of the mechanized industrial age turning.
As the story goes, Reif developed a device for Timkin's factory that saved millions of dollars a year in production costs. A scanning machine for establishing the quality of the steel used in manufacturing the ball bearings.
This x-ray scanner detected flaws in the steel supply before it was sent to the production line, and in doing so, significantly increased the efficiency and output of the factory.
Timkin was so impressed with Reif and so grateful for his brilliant innovation that he rewarded Reif with his full sponsorship.
Reif took up residence on the Timkin estate in San Diego, and there, in a room above the garage, he was lavishly supplied with whatever equipment or money he needed to outfit an entire laboratory.
Henry Timkin's sister, Amelia Bridges, shared his regard for Reif, and before long, she, too, became his patron.
We've heard reports that Amelia Bridges would visit the lab, ask him if he needed anything, and just simply write out a check.
So whatever he wanted, whether it was a new x-ray machine or machine tools for constructing instruments, they built a custom lab, which was specifically designed for the type of experiments that he wanted to do.
So he was in a unique position to accomplish some of these revolutionary things.
Reif was a master tool maker, and he knew a tremendous amount about optics.
He was also visionary in his approach. He fought outside the box, he drew outside the lines, and that's why he created something that no one has duplicated since then.
I mean, when you talk with people who are supposedly the experts on microscopy, they say, oh, that's impossible.
Of course, the world was flat at one time, too, and the Earth had everything, all the planets revolving around it at one time, too, and then everything changed.
All of a sudden, everything was revolving around the Sun, and the Earth was round.
Why leave the conventional microscope that we have in our hands at the present time in our laboratories can be kept at a point where it is at the present time?
That's why I designed this built piece of the instrument, because I was stopped. I was against the stone wall, and I couldn't do any more.
Well, Reif had to build his microscopes out of necessity, really, because using the conventional instruments, he was unable to see the microorganisms that he knew existed from other experiments.
So, in addition, in order to determine if you're destroying a microorganism, you have to be able to view it in its live state.
So, that's really why he began and finally built his special microscopes, which were able to view the minutest organisms in the live state.
A key point is the Smithsonian article published in 1944. Here, the electron microscope was announced along with the Reif microscope.
Now, both of them could see viruses for the first time, but the difference was that Reif could see it as a movie, and the electron microscope saw it as a photograph.
Now, if you're trying to understand an organism, it's helpful to see a photograph of something, but it's much more helpful to see it as a movie, because things change over time.
Reif was able to see the microscope in its live state.
Over a course of 20 years, Reif constructed a series of five microscopes, all of which were referred to as virus microscopes, because of their ability to view these minut organisms in a live state.
But how did these instruments achieve what the laws of optics define as impossible?
You cannot stain those particles with your acid manuel and dye stain.
Except as I've stated a thousand times that the particles are smaller than the molecular portions or the granular structure of your acid manuel and dye stain, so the mousey can't swallow the elephant.
Naturally, they can only be stained with a frequency of light.
You use a monochromatic light because a monochromatic light is a portion of the spectrum.
So when you get light in the same range or a corresponding range, it will cause those microorganisms to fluoresce.
That's something that people hadn't really done before or since.
You use monochromatic light to investigate microorganisms and determine species specificity, a specific species of a microorganism.
One of the other working principles about it was that the way that it channels the light never allows the beams of light to cross over themselves and create diffusion of the light.
So you continue to have your resolution no matter how far you take the light path, you're not losing resolution.
Below the key features of the Rife Virus Microscope is that they had superior magnification with corresponding resolution.
And also another important factor was the contrast that with his special illumination system, he was able to produce contrast in the organisms without chemical stains.
And even when identifying the organisms because of the way they're illuminating and the contrast that's produced with the so-called monochromatic light, you could identify which virus you're looking at by the color that it refracted.
So that had never been done and probably still hasn't been done today.
And so these key features of the microscope, which were far superior to what was available at the time, allowed him to discover things that other people were unable to because they simply lacked the equipment.
We're bringing the answer up clear up to 50,000 times magnification we have photographs of those that will show that the tiny cell is composed of a series of little cells.
And the little cells again are higher magnifications that we bring up to 5,000 times.
At the 10,000 times we see that the cells within the cells are composed of a series of little cells.
We bring it all up and we separate it down and we keep that little point growing up, as I say, to 60,000 times.
And we wonder where infinity is.
The universal microscope was a revolutionary breakthrough in optics altogether.
And it's a very simple principle, what allows it to actually work.
And it's amazing that no one has discovered it before then or reinvented it since then because it isn't really outside the reach of technology that we have at all.
It's fairly simple technology.
It's just that the funding hasn't been there at the same time that the expertise has been there to do the work.
Everything vibrates at its own frequency.
vibrates at its own frequency.
If you have a crystalline protein structure involved
and you always do in microorganisms,
you can even set up Hermione resonance
by bombarding it with frequencies
as long as you're within the right ranges of frequencies.
And that will literally shatter the crystalline protein
structure.
It's coordinate resonance.
As I say, you take two tuning forks that pitch to the sear
and the absolute issue at one and the other one resonates.
So where's your electronic frequency?
It's through the tissues of the body
that simply devaluatizes the bacteria
with no harm to normal tissue.
I found lethal frequencies for at least 24 microorganisms.
I say 24 because we have copies of his lab notes
with those 24 microorganisms.
He reportedly found frequencies for many more.
For instance, we have tuberculosis, syphilis,
gonorrhea, streptococcal bacteria,
staphylococcal bacteria,
typhoid, all sorts of microorganisms
can be destroyed with the correct frequency.
As an inventor myself, I mean, I hold three patents,
and I build robotic systems.
I understand the complexity of bringing new technology to market,
but I also understand the market value
of this kind of invention.
And the fact that the vested interests of pharmaceutical companies
be very, very threatened
by the fact that we have a very, very good technology
and we have a very, very good technology.
The vested interests of pharmaceutical companies
be very, very threatened
as such a technology came out.
And science has always had a problem.
They've always had this problem
that true breakthroughs will destroy
the entire financial structure which exists.
So it's just not going to happen.
I mean, the funding will disappear,
the government will clamp down.
This happens over and over and over again.
You know, there are some of these people
that you talk to them.
And the more you talk to them,
the more you try to explain anything
to them, the more they get riled up.
You know, I'll tell you.
And Dr. Johnson, you know why we went through a lot of that stuff,
and we checked the thing out completely
from one end to the other,
and we classified a frequency
for an individual bacteria
as the individual water loss military rate.
Because when I check on that thing
and look through that microscope
an hour after an hour, day after day,
tuning that thing, I just find something
that's going to kill that bug.
And every hour, half an hour, whatever is required,
I put a new fresh culture under the microscope
and keep that on.
And I find something that folds it up.
All right.
Then I go back to zero to the end,
then you come back up to my settings
and put another fresh culture in it.
If it will do it,
10 or 12 consecutive times,
and that is recorded.
And using a simple electromagnetic wave
is probably not sufficient.
Dr. Reif found that using a wave
that is emitted by a gas
within a glass tube
that has been excited by radio frequency energy,
that particular wave that's emanated from that tube
is a wave that is acceptable to the tissues of the body
for whatever reason.
And it will penetrate deep within the body
and can be used to selectively
oscillate those particular things that
the doctor or Dr. Reif, in this case,
chose to oscillate
and leave everything else alone in the body.
And that's a wonder of it all,
is that you have this selective,
scalpel-like effect using resonance.
It's specific, it leaves everything else alone.
It's really quite an amazing, wondrous feat.
The people that worked with Reif weren't amateurs.
I mean, Dr. Rosna was called
one of the greatest bacteriologists
in the history of the Mayo Clinic.
Dr. Kendall was referred to as America's Pasteur.
Now, some people might consider that an insult,
but nonetheless, that's the highest honor
that one could be accorded.
Dr. Milbank Johnson was head
of the local medical society in California.
Some of the physicists, I think,
Coolidge assisted him.
We've had reports that C.P. Steinmetz
assisted him with some of the work.
Even Lee DeForest, who is credited
with inventing the vacuum tube triode,
was reportedly involved with Reif.
So these people knew what they were doing.
And I think if they weren't really impressed
with what Reif was doing,
I don't think they would have stayed with him
as long as they did.
What I've been able to determine, Kendall,
Rosna, Johnson, and other people like this,
were all top of their field.
They were well respected within their field of medicine
here in the United States.
Dr. Kendall, he was certainly
a cardiologist, as was Dr. Rosenau.
All these people were well published, highly respected.
Rosenau was head of his department
in the Mayo Clinic, for goodness sakes.
This is not a minor position to be appointed to.
Dr. Johnson was well respected
at the University of Southern California.
And he certainly was an individual
well respected within his own medical community
where he worked.
He was able to, just by asking people
through his influence and their respect for him
as an individual in credibility,
get other medical doctors involved in this work.
I think that says a lot.
On the weekend following the calamitous stock market crash
of 1929, Reif emerged into the public eye.
The fruits of nearly 20 years of mind-boggling work
were presented for the first time
in this front-page headline story.
Before this time, Reif had worked in private,
occasionally seeking consultation
with the leading minds in optics and electronics
in a drive to perfect his instruments
and his laboratory techniques.
After the existence of his super microscope
became widely known, the tables turned
and the experts began seeking consultation with Reif.
Some of America's top bacteriologists
read a pathway directly to Reif's lab.
There was a major debate raging in microbiology at the time
and it was believed that a microscope like Reif's
might just settle it.
The debate hinged upon the question of the existence
and controversial nature of a certain kind of microorganism
referred to as a filterable form of bacteria,
so-called because it was so small and plastic
through the minute pores of a stone filter,
too small to be seen with any conventional microscope.
These very fine porcelain filters,
available in different grades of porosity,
are generally used in microbiology
to isolate virus-sized microbes.
The controversy arose when a number of bacteriologists
claimed that they could take a fluid
from a growth culture of a large bacteria
and after passing that fluid through a filter
and placing the emerging liquid on a culture media or food,
they could cultivate or regrow the original bacteria again.
Conventional microbiologists considered this result
to be due to leaky filters or contaminated samples
and regarded the notion of a filterable form of bacteria
as absurd.
However, the findings of some filtrationist microbiologists
were much more upsetting than the proposed caterpillar
to butterfly-type transition between some types of bacteria
and their much smaller filterable forms.
Some filtrationists had discovered that by changing the food
or culture media, they could encourage transitions
from one filterable form into many different types of organisms,
all of them a different species than the bacteria
that originally produced the filterable form.
If this were true, it would shake the foundations of microbiology
and force a complete rewrite of our textbooks.
The man who pioneered this obscure branch of microbiology
known as pleomorphism was the French pathologist Antoine O'Shaugh.
In his time, O'Shaugh was an authoritative presence
renowned for his exacting laboratory methods,
his precise thinking, and his vast knowledge in microbiology.
He was one of France's greatest scientists.
His contributions included discovering a method
of dramatically reducing the cost of producing aniline dye,
thereby revolutionizing the entire French garment industry.
He discovered the causes of fermentation in 1855
and in 1862 he found the causes of certain rampant diseases of grapes
which were then ravaging the French wine industry.
In 1865 he saved the garment industry again
by finding the cause of an epidemic disease
that was destroying the silkworm population of Europe.
Yet, astonishingly, O'Shaugh was not credited
with his successes.
Most of his work, in fact, was plagiarized
by a rival French scientist, one Louis Pasteur.
It was Louis Pasteur who received recognition
for determining that fermentation was caused by a microorganism
and that the silkworm disease was due to a parasite
and that grapes were being consumed via bacteria.
In her book, O'Shaugh or Pasteur,
historian Ethel Hume demonstrates that these discoveries
were absolutely attributed to the wrong man.
O'Shaugh and Pasteur were rivals,
both of them associates at France's Academies of Science.
Even a cursory examination of their discourses
and their very public arguments
were readily revealed who was the gifted scientist
and who was the impostor.
Ironically, history has dubbed Louis Pasteur
as the founder of the germ theory of disease,
the idea that infection is the primary pathway to illness,
a paradigm that rose and endured
more out of political considerations
than through an unbiased scientific inquiry.
O'Shaugh was investigating a proposition
that was much more complex than a simple infection model.
In essence, O'Shaugh believed that the emerging germ theory
of disease was incomplete.
O'Shaugh's exacting techniques in the laboratory
had revealed where he believed
to be an elementary living part of the disease.
O'Shaugh's exacting techniques in the laboratory
had revealed where he believed
to be an elementary living particle.
He called it the microzyma,
an extremely tiny living organism
capable of transforming into many different pathogenic forms
as a result of changes in the chemical makeup
of its host environment.
With O'Shaugh's discovery of this tendency
for his so-called microzyma to change forms,
the study of pleomorphism was founded.
Whereas Pasteur has remembered for his germ theory of disease,
which is arguably not even his original theory,
O'Shaugh and his theory of pleomorphism
has been generally forgotten.
But not by everyone,
not by a growing number of microbiologists
who have taken the time to experiment
with new culture mediums,
advanced microscopes, and living specimens.
Dr. Arthur Isaac Kendall was a filtrationist.
He believed he had found the very media
that would allow bacteria to transform
into their tiny, filterable state.
He called it the K-media.
And this is where one of O'Shaugh's collaborators
was very well known back in his time,
the Kendall media, the K-media.
I don't know what all was in it,
but the specific contents of media
would influence what the growth patterns would be,
or the lack of growth.
Dr. Kendall was in need of a special microscope himself
for the work that he was doing,
so he contacted an associate in California,
Dr. Milbank Johnson,
and asked him if such a microscope actually existed.
So, upon inquiry, Dr. Johnson found out
that, in fact, the microscope did exist,
and Dr. Kendall immediately made arrangements
to visit Dr. Reif and to collaborate with him.
Reif was having his own difficulties.
Despite enormous progress in his instrument refinements,
he was having no success finding
his proposed cancer microbe.
First, I begin sectioning tissues
of every known type of malignancy.
I sectioned over 20,000 of those,
cut them down with a special microtone
to raise them, some of them were only a microaltingness.
I studied those under the microscope,
and I eventually built my first high-powered microscope
for the purpose of analyzing and checking those sections.
The only result that I obtained over all those years was
I succeeded in developing a very excellent technique
of tissue preparation,
but I never found an organism that I could say
was the cause of an agent of malignancy.
So, because Reif was unable to culture
any of those so-called filterable organisms
on his own, it was extremely fortuitous
that he met Dr. Kendall,
and Dr. Kendall brought his medium to Reif,
and Reif brought his special microscope to Kendall,
so this unique collaboration allowed them
to do things that they couldn't do individually.
And we succeeded definitely in isolating
a filterable form of that bacteria,
using a Kendall media,
it's known as Kendall media.
Now, that is what Kendall used for the isolation
or bringing out this bacillus typhosis
in the filterable state,
and that is what Kendall used for the isolation
and bringing out this bacillus typhosis
in the filterable state,
which is published in the California Western Medicine
in 1931, our joint report on that.
We find that the bacillus typhosis
in its filterable state
is a beautiful turquoise blue body.
We see them swimming through the field,
they're highly multiple.
The transformation of your terminal
or what we term the transitional state
of these organisms is accomplished
by the media form which we grow them, that's all.
Because we can change these organisms
readily by the media form which we grow them,
from one organism to another,
as long as their organism belongs in the same category
or what we term the same group
as a series of organisms.
What I believe is that
some of these new pathogenic organisms
we have with us at all time,
our metabolism changes,
so, same as I say, I could take a colon bacillus
in 36 hours, I could make an end to a typhoid bacillus
by lowering the media to part per million per volume.
Right now, whenever they have no reaction
of a typhoid bacillus,
we don't react, have it.
The whole thing straight through.
I sure don't sound like what I learned in my college.
By the end of 1931,
Reif and Kenville have demonstrated
that a filterable organism
could be cultured out of the typhoid bacillus
using K-media as a nutrient
and that this and other filterable organisms
could be seen glowing in their own natural color
through a Reif microscope.
Their findings were widely publicized
and it would have been difficult
for any attentive bacteriologist
to have missed the exciting news
of this fundamental discovery in the field
or its implications.
The man who introduced Kenville and Reif,
Dr. Milbank Johnson,
understood the politics of science and medicine.
He was well aware that Reif and Kenville's findings
would not, in the end,
be accepted by the mere weight of science journal articles.
In 1931, there was only one
Reif virus microscope in full operation
and that microscope stayed with Reif.
Also, not only was K-media tricky to make,
its use required considerable skill and patience.
Johnson felt a demonstration was necessary.
He held a dinner at his Pasadena mansion
to honor Kendall and Reif
and give the cream of America's medical scientists
a first-hand look at their achievements.
This well-attended occasion was announced
as a dinner to celebrate the end of all disease.
Following these developments came a simple blood test
that could be used to diagnose patients
with typhoid fever weeks before any symptoms arose.
And Reif found the frequency that would destroy this micro
or revitalize it, as Reif would explain.
But it was not enough.
Finally, the voice of conventional microbiology,
the most powerful man in the field,
Dr. Thomas Rivers of the Rockefeller Institute,
spoke out against Kendall's findings.
At a medical symposium in 1932
at Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore,
Rivers and his associate Hans Zinsser of Harvard
publicly challenged Kendall's filtration experiments,
stating that they could not repeat them
and therefore the findings of Kendall were invalid.
Not once in their discourse did Rivers or Zinsser
express any scientific curiosity toward this new microscope,
a microscope that was introduced in the same papers
that announced the isolation of the filterable forms.
It was as if the scientific community
didn't want to know about it.
And this symposium marked the advent of official denial
to which the rank-and-file scientists of the day
dutifully fell behind.
But there were other microbiologists
who were not swayed by Rivers' authority
or the threat of his censure.
Dr. Edward Rosenau, chief bacteriologist
at the renowned Mayo Clinic,
was a man who would become a pleomorphist
as a result of his findings.
Rosenau had discovered a pleomorphic relationship
between the Streptococcus bacillus
and the much smaller poliovirus.
He sought out Rife and his microscope
to help him confirm this relationship.
He worked with him when he was 14 years old
on poliovirus.
He was there in the Department of Research
about the origin of his own blood changes.
And he said they wanted his rapid apartment.
I said, hold everything.
They said, I'm coming back.
We went short.
And he was a great surgeon on Streptococcus.
Because he worked almost entirely
on an autopsy and passing.
We proved those.
All of us don't do the disease
in the lymphatic chain of the albino rat.
I found the organ in it.
He had an article that was published
in the Mayo Clinic July 13th in 1932.
It's right in there.
You can see it, Rosenau.
We went short.
We ran this thing through.
We showed him the motion pictures.
I've done the whole entire process.
I let him.
Then they fired Rosenau.
He was getting too close.
You know, it's a terrible thing to talk like that.
But I'm not there.
But I'm sick of that.
But I'll tell you this right now.
I may get shot later for saying it.
But most microscopists,
most people using microscopes
in the United States,
I'm not saying about Canada,
Australia, any other country,
but here in the United States,
most of the microscopy
that pathologists do,
you know, they're doing it
at the very lowest level
of technical skill
that you can imagine.
Although I will have to admit,
things have improved a little bit
in the last 10 or 15 years.
But 40 years ago,
most of the microscopy
was very poor.
It was just good enough
that you could make a cognitive diagnosis.
You could send that in,
get it entered in the records,
and you could send the pill out for it.
The lines are blurrier today
than they were even at that time
in micro-organism developments.
Because of new equipment,
there's more that's seen than before.
But what's happening is that
all this emerging information
is creating a revolution in the field.
And now people are dealing with things
that they didn't even know existed
even 10 years ago,
microplasmas, nanobacteria,
bacteria that are smaller than viruses.
People don't even know how to classify
what they're looking at.
It is such a chaotic soup.
And there isn't a lot of money
that goes into research around it.
It's a highly undefined field
we're having to actually...
I mean, there's been a language
that's had to be invented even
to talk about some of these things,
to even name them.
Here's one thing you'll find,
and you'll find it in years and years
of experience, John,
that it's an absolute true statement
that I've found out over all the years
I've worked with this work
and I've worked hard
and sincerely along the street.
You'll find by God that
nine-tenths of the criticism
is a cloak of ignorance.
When they don't know themselves,
then it ain't the voice.
The concept of a virus,
as we understand it today,
originated with Dr. Thomas Rivers,
who, in 1926,
authoritatively stated
that a virus can only grow
within the pre-existing metabolism
of a host cell.
It has become a major plank of virology
that a virus will not propagate
upon an artificial culture media.
It must be placed on a live tissue media
or a host organism in order to develop.
But before virology became a science,
the term virus was used to denote
any pathogenic microorganism
that was one order smaller
than a bacteria,
too small to be seen.
Micro-microorganisms were viruses,
from the Latin term meaning poison.
Rife used the term in its archaic sense
because his understanding of microbiology
widely differed from what was emerging in the field.
To rife, viruses were the minute
filterable forms of the much larger bacteria.
The two organisms married
in a pleomorphic relationship.
To conventional microbiologists,
viruses and bacteria are not related,
except in the sense that one needs the other
to exist, in a manner that Rivers denoted
in 1926.
Most of them disregarded pleomorphism as fallacy,
recalling the primacy of pastures,
germ theory of disease,
and the spectacle of Thomas Rivers
publicly shutting down Dr. Kendall
in the early 1930s.
Today, microbiology dictates that it would be impossible
to cultivate a cancer virus
out of an artificial culture media,
but that is exactly what Royal Raymond Rife
claimed to do in 1932.
The present-day definition of a virus
notwithstanding.
But I kept at the work,
and I succeeded in
eventually isolating a virus.
In order to prove
the causation of disease
by microorganism,
microbiologists use a set of standards
known as
In order to prove
the causation of disease
by microorganism,
microbiologists use a set of standards
known as
coax postulates.
And basically what these say is that
an organism should be isolated
from a diseased patient,
cultured in a pure culture,
and it should be isolated
from a diseased patient,
cultured in a pure culture,
infecting an animal model,
and then recovering
that same organism while producing
that same disease in the animal.
And this is what Rife did.
He took a human breast tumor,
he cultured it with the special K medium,
and the culturing technique
that he had developed,
and then proceeded to inject it
into lab rats,
and then produced massive tumors
in these rats, and then recovered
microorganism from those rats.
So he was probably the first
and maybe only person
to fulfill coax postulates
for a cancer-causing microorganism.
We take this BX.
We have.
I slid it directly from a non-slided breast mass.
We ordered a medium.
We no longer have
what we call a BX,
we have what we call a BY.
This will no longer pass
the WB from where we use it,
much coarser for nothing or the M.
So, all right.
Now we order the medium again
and we find a monoconarrate organism.
This organism can be seen
readily with a good research microscope.
With a proper standing and met,
and we find it only
in the monocytes of the blood.
Now, we order the medium once again.
We come from our fluid medias
into a hard-baked submedia.
We use iris, fragrance or tomato
when we're on board.
We no longer have here
a BX.
We no longer have a BY.
We no longer have a monoconarrate organism
that we find in the monocytes
of the white zone of the blood,
but we have a cryptomyces
pleomorphia fungi.
Well, its 14 states
is clear from the
regional hyphae up through the spores
on the Aztec school all the time.
Any one of these
can be shown back in 24 hours
into a BX,
when we have that monoconarrate
and produce the disease.
Knowledge of this fungal
transitional state came to rife
through independent research
being conducted by another bacteriologist,
Dr. Cameron Gruner
of Canada.
His microbiological research
tended toward pleomorphism
and with this approach
Gruner was beginning to crack the cancer
puzzle.
It was all a matter of the medium.
Gruner's media
was based upon an asparagus agar
which grew a fungus
of cancerous blood.
Kendall's media, which rife used
was a protein broth
which grew a virus out of cancerous tissue.
When rife and Gruner collaborated
in the 1930s
with the tools of rife's laboratory
to aid them, they discovered
the following remarkable facts.
When a sample of Gruner's fungus
was cultured on K-media,
the so-called BX virus
emerged.
They could and effect by changing
the media turned a fungus
originally grown out of cancerous blood
into the virus-sized BX
organism, itself
grown out of cancerous tissue.
To further
confirm the connection, they
tried culturing rife's BX
in Gruner's asparagus agar.
The result
BX changed into
Gruner's fungus.
These experiments were repeated
hundreds of times and in the end
they left no doubt
in the mind of rife or Gruner.
There is a microorganism
associated with cancer
and it is, by nature,
pleomorphic.
So he conceived of the idea
of putting the organisms
into an oscillating electromagnetic field
and causing them
to oscillate similar to the way
a glass oscillates when it's hit
with an appropriate audio tone.
So he was looking for
an electrical frequency that would
cause the microorganism
to shatter or to be
divided in some sense.
So what he first did was he tried
the various wavelengths
such as light to ultraviolet,
infrared, he tried them all
and finally he came upon a range
of frequencies which is in the radio range
that cause the destruction
of these microorganisms
and the frequencies are specific
to each species.
Music
By the end of 1932,
Rife had isolated a virus
from cancer.
He had developed a unique
to sustain it
and to make it visible.
He had fully explored
its various physical properties
and had discovered additional
transitional forms of the microbe.
He had transplanted it
into laboratory animals
producing the disease conditions
resulting in tumor growth
and then he had found
the mortal oscillatory rate
of the virus and destroyed it
with his beam ray instrument
but one test remained.
Could the beam tube
kill the microorganism inside
the body of a host?
Rife had established annihilation
of the virus in vitro
but could it be done in vivo
and further,
if it killed the organism,
would it cure the disease?
Pliomorphists like Rife
believe that the relationship between
a germ and a disease
is more complex than a simple
cause and effect arrangement.
As we have seen,
the arrival of a microorganism in a body
does not necessarily always come
from an external source
but may instead be, as some claim,
the result of a pliomorphic
transition from another form
of the germ that is already inside the body.
Would this complicate
the notion of killing the germ
and thus curing the disease?
I guess without pathic medicine though
in the germ theory the basis says
that we are attacked by external
microbes, viruses, bacteria
and anything in between
and that's what's
affecting our body.
Pliomorphists would say that
if the environment is right in our body
yeah that can happen
but at the same time any existing microbes
in our body can have evolved
to a higher pathological form
and create disease.
So as we pull our bodies more and more
with physical toxins, emotional toxins
etc. I think it lays
the foundation for disease development
where one micro can be a virus
of bacteria or a fungal form
depending on its environment.
That sounds very controversial.
Of course, it turns
the foundation of medicine into the germ theory.
Well, we did analyze
and by this frequency
in the work we've done
this far with this thing
but
here is the thing
the effect
of data sees
on an individual
depends
greatly
upon the balance of the metabolism
of that individual
from the neutral pH
but I sincerely believe
that the body is
in an absolute normal pH
susceptible to no disease
because an artiste
will show that the body
can grow on a neutral pH
regardless of what kind of media
but it may be whatever it is.
So what it means is you have to have
a pre-existing condition
in the terrain for the microorganism
to take root or take hold
and then the microorganism
will then
to make its own environment
more permanently.
They do this by producing
their own species-specific acids
they convert acids
that come into the system
into, for instance, mucoracemosis
would convert it to lactic acid
and aspergillus niger
would convert it to citric acid
but these are the acids that they use
in their environment
they're their nutritive medium
so they can be considered
a machine like this
a surgery for treating a patient
who is considered to far advance
for surgery.
Yes, because of
not 16 cases we had to avoid
even imagine what they gave it to
they came on antlers
even imagine what they gave it.
So with the successful animal
experiments that Reif conducted
then Dr. Johnson convinced him
that they should do a trial
and Reif was hesitant at first
but then consented
on the condition that a team
of medical specialists would be involved
so
with Dr. Johnson's supervision
and under the auspices of
the University of Southern California
they formed a special research committee
and in 1934
they took 16
terminally ill patients
and within a period of 3 months
successfully treated all of them.
So, as I say
the results we've had
have been very encouraging
we had a clinic in 1934
in La Jolla, Dr. William Johnson
this was
one of the
big brands
that was an English life insurance company
and one of many of them
is a medical politician
and he had to be quick
because that is what he was going to say
so
he didn't want to go but he said
alright, let's go here
and when he shortly after
was Ellen Scripps died out there
and he went to the whole Ellen Scripps
only when a clinic out there
we were there 90 days
we actually were not planning about
I would say 70 days
we did actual clinical work
and first I told him
I wanted to do a legitimate order
and I said I want you to
surround on this committee
that will set
for the biggest man in the United States
that's a Euro politician
and as he's been doing that
he got Bishop of New York
he got William Morris
he got George Johnson
that's what happened
and so on
and as I said, that was
our pathologist
that one of Ellen Scripps
who's the friend of both of us
of course
I said, I want you to organize this special medical research committee under the Bonaparte University,
which we did under the University of Southern California, Dr. Johnson.
He came to wait there, too.
We did it during the clinic.
We got through.
We had already put photographs before and after.
At the end of the time, we had our meeting.
Well, that was, that was a little better why this board turned out 14 of our exclusively cured.
14 of the 16 patients were successfully treated in the first 70 days,
and the remaining two were pronounced cured by Dr. James Couch
after three more weeks' treatment with Rife's beam ray.
Dr. Couch describes his impressions.
When I was told about this, Dr. Royal Rife, and I had a machine out at the Scripps Institute,
I went out to see about it and became very much interested in seeing the cases which he had.
And the thing that brought me into it more quickly than anything was a man who had a cancer in the stomach.
This was a man who staggered into a table just on the brass end of gas.
It was a bag of bones.
That's the ray on the bed.
Dr. Rife dealt with my cancer, said, just feel that man's stomach, doctor.
So I put my hand on his stomach, which was a warm, solid, hard mass,
about just what I could cover with my hand.
And it was absolutely solid.
And I thought, well, nothing can be done for that.
However, they gave him a treatment of the Rife frequencies.
And in the course of time, to my astonishment, he completely recovered.
How many times and what was the extent of each treatment, Dr. Rife?
Well, we used three minutes on each treatment.
And we found the patients between it twice a week.
We got better results than when we treated every day, simply because when we worked down,
you know, revitalized this virus or organism in the tissues of the body,
can't get the lymphatic system a chance to absorb it and take it up and cast it all.
We treated half of them every day and half of them twice a week.
And the last we treated twice a week, we got better results.
The following years saw a tireless push by Dr. Johnson
as he sought to have Rife's work in cancer independently verified in other laboratories.
They approached the Hooper Foundation and the International Cancer Research Foundation
to prestigious institutions which had the money and the clout
to proceed seriously with the work.
And there was an advanced laboratory in New Jersey operated by Dr. John Burnett,
a man who had more than a professional association with Rife.
Well, Dr. Burnett's connection to Rife was through his wife, who was one of the Tenkin sisters.
And so Burnett was also a well-known researcher.
And his laboratory was probably, you know, almost equal to Rife's.
And he was doing research to verify Rife's work and other fields of electromedicine.
Where independent verification of the work was concerned,
it was only Dr. Burnett who continued with Rife in good faith.
The other research organizations after a flurry of initial enthusiasm
wasted years of time by embroiling Rife and Johnson
in an endless barrage of bureaucratic red tape.
It seemed that the Hooper Foundation and the International Cancer Research Foundation
were more concerned with satisfying the whims of impatient board members
than following the rigors of clearly established experimental science.
And what have they ever spent?
What have they ever spent or anything?
Fertilio did buy a couple iron rods.
And for the cancer outfit, they spent by God less than $50,000 out of their $127 million
that they've got in part as a rest.
But what are they doing with it?
Drashto, my dear John, $50,000 only equipped with Spatterass laboratory.
Oh, I guess they're using it to subsidize their own operation.
Well, they... Jesus Christ.
All businesses were as smart as they were. They might have some more success.
Yeah. No, but Jesus Christ.
I'm kind of stuck on people paying their good money.
They're paying their good money toward the contribution that they think
is going to be so benefit to humanity and more than they ever go.
It's a personal place.
That's the cost of working in the cost. We've lost millions of people.
All the cities that could have been healed by a rights machine.
We are losing a quarter of a million people every year on cancer right now.
This is a published figure.
Of course, the American Medical Association standard
requires that there be at least five years of successful operation
The successful cancer clinic in La Jolla demanded two necessary courses of action, one to get
independent verification of the microbiology involved, a cooperation that was proving quite
difficult for Dr. Johnson to engineer.
The other necessary course of action was obvious, more experimental therapy on sick
people with the beam ram.
So with that initial success, Dr. Johnson also ran clinics of his own where he treated
a variety of diseases including even cataracts and tuberculosis and various illnesses and
there was also a few other doctors, there was one doctor named James Couch who ran the
machine in his clinics and had astounding success.
There was one Dr. Hamer who was treating about 40 patients a day.
As a matter of fact, he was so busy using the machine that he had to hire a couple of
technicians to run the machines.
Dr. Reif evaluated 34 and approved it conclusively and it was absolutely perfected then, the process
lingered and then Nobel bank Johnson took it up to Pasadena and run some more clinical
tests 36, 37 which were very successful.
Now the original Reif machines were effective but they were massive and unmanageable.
So Reif wanted to build a new series of instruments that would not only be more modern with the
advancements of electronics but be more compact and manageable so that they could be used
in a clinical setting.
So Dr. Johnson brought an electrical engineer named Philip Hoylund in and with his help they
built the new instruments that were used by the doctors in their clinics.
He is a repair worker and in fact I think Hoylund in those early days made up for life about
three experimental instruments.
The basic principle of the devices is the same as it was in the initial state.
Now we can see that there is no getting around or a loop on any coordinate with but the improvement
has been in the field of electronics itself in the devices that we can obtain such as
tools and transformers and rectifiers and shocks and appliances and whatnot that are installed
in there, you see.
Clearly improved over the old religion up, the old religion up, and so on and so on.
It appears that Philip Hoylund joined the ranks of the Reif Research Lab shortly after
the first cancer clinic in La Jolla.
As an employee of Reif's his job was strictly that of electronics engineer with the task
of modernizing the old equipment.
However soon after becoming immersed in the work his involvement became much more personal
and ambitious.
One of which was a correspondent school called the United Polytechnical Institute.
To speed up their own incorporation Hutchinson proposed to retool his already existing school
and rename it Beam Raise Incorporated.
The others went along with the idea not recognizing the pitfalls of such an arrangement for the
persons, some of whom had given Hutchinson money and others who were tied to him through
his previously owned corporations.
There was also the hard reality that the Beam Raise stock itself was practically worthless.
The company owned no patent on the device that they manufactured.
On its own the Beam Raise machine was unpatentable.
The problem was how does one sell this device together with the frequencies that it uses
to kill microorganisms without divulging the frequencies themselves.
Philip Hoylund came up with a solution.
He decided to hide the frequencies within the circuitry of the machine so that the dial
settings would not indicate the true frequencies but an encoded numeric equivalent.
And then he changed the way the machine itself generated those frequencies so that nosy engineers
could be hard pressed to determine what was intended as an output.
As it turned out it was a bad idea.
As Ray pointed out in a 1929 article, when money comes in the door, science goes out the window.
So it's much like what happened with the Beam Raise corporation.
Once the money came in, the greed and the infighting just destroyed itself.
At some point in time Philip Hoylund began making changes and modifications to the instruments
that were fundamentally different than what Ray was doing.
And that's when the machines began to fail to produce positive results.
And that's also when the troubles in the Beam Raise corporation began.
When we were complaining we can't sell these things on those days old.
We had reason to believe we failed and we didn't believe it.
The disparity of developing trouble was being brought on by Hoylund as part of the scheme that brings up the others.
And which must depend on some cooperation from Hutchins.
This schism in the company was made most evident when a group of British doctors expressed interest in Rife's work.
Dr. Winter Gonen, personal physician to King George, heard about the whole affair through Dr. Couch, an associate of Rife's.
Gonen and his associates wanted to acquire a Rife microscope and a Beam Raise device to take back to England for testing.
The contentious question became, is the British group dealing with the Beam Raise corporation or is it dealing with the Rife Research Laboratory?
The Rife Research Laboratory
Well, nobody was ever sure whether Hoylund deliberately sabotaged.
Well, nobody was ever sure whether Hoylund deliberately sabotaged the machines that they sent to England or whether it was just an incompetent bugler.
I have seen Dr. Gonen's correspondence on them.
He complained that they weren't even booked up.
The components weren't even wired together properly.
Yeah, our own suspicion at the time was that it was deliberate sabotage because Hutchins and Hoylund already were planning to take over the thing for themselves.
You see, they had it figured out.
If they could ease Rife out, then they would have time to steal from each other at their leisure later.
But the first thing to do was to get rid of the poor, unsuspecting life.
The Rife Research Laboratory